<!-- manpage 1daq -->
      <refentry id="daq1-evbclientfw-run">
        <refmeta>
           <refentrytitle id="daq1-evbclientfw-run-title">Event builder client framework</refentrytitle>
           <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
        </refmeta>
        <refnamediv>
           <refname>Event builder client framework</refname>
           <refpurpose>Event builder cilent framework</refpurpose>
        </refnamediv>
        
        <refsynopsisdiv>
          <cmdsynopsis>    
          <command>
<replaceable>binary-name options...</replaceable>
          </command>
          </cmdsynopsis>

        </refsynopsisdiv>
        <refsect1>
           <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
           <para>
            The end result of user code build on top of the event builder
            clienty framework is a runnable program.  The program uses
            a .ggo file to define the set of options it supports.
            Several options are defined for use by the framework, others
            shared between the framework and your application code, while
            you may add other options to the skeleton .ggo files for
            purely application specific purposes.
           </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
           <title>
              OPTIONS
           </title>
           <para>
            The options described here are those that are defined in the
            skeleton .ggo file.
           </para>
           <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--evbhost</option>=<replaceable>hostname</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides the name of the host on which the event
                            orderer/event builder is running.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--evbport</option>=<replaceable>port-spec</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Provides a specification of the port number on which
                            the event orderer is listening for connections.
                            If <literal>managed</literal> is used, the
                            software will attempt to locate the server's
                            port using the remote system's port manager.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--info</option>=<replaceable>information string</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            When connecting to the event builder/orderer,
                            this string is used to describe the connection.
                            It is available to GUI software that has been
                            incorporated in the event orderer.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--ids</option>=<replaceable>id-list</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Normally this is a comma separated list of the
                            event source ids that are managed by this
                            data source.  Ring buffers comprise only a single
                            event source and the program quits with an error
                            if more than one event source id is supplied.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The event source id tags each fragment submitted
                            to the event builder. This allows data consumers
                            to know which fragment came from which data source.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
          

           </variablelist>
        </refsect1>

      </refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->